Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution
Mary Margaret Sittig research material on Louis Prang
1860-1978
Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution
Sittig, Mary Margaret
3.5 linear feet
Art historian Mary Margaret Sittig's research material on Louis Prang dates from 1860 to 1978 and measures 3.5 linear feet. Found within the papers are biographical material for Louis Prang and for Mary Margaret Sittig, collected letters from various members of the Prang family, and scattered letters to Sittig from friends. Additional collected research materials include scattered personal business records for Louis Prang and his wife, notes and writings, art work, printed material, and photographs.
Provenance
The papers were donated by Mary Margaret Sittig's brother James C. Sittig in 2001, in memory of Charlotte, Edgar, and Mary Sittig.
Related Material
The Archives also holds the Louis Prang papers, 1848-1932.
Restrictions on Access
Use of original papers requires an appointment.
Biographical Note
Mary Margaret Sittig was a doctoral student at George Washington University in Washington D.C. working on a dissertation about the life and work of Boston lithographer Louis Prang (1824-1909), often referred to as the "father of the American Christmas card." Sittig completed her Master's theses L. Prang and Company, Fine Art Publishers in 1970, but died before completing her doctoral dissertation.
In 1864, Prang visited Europe to study the latest techniques in German lithography. He returned to Boston to create high quality reproductions of major works of art using a lithographic process he called "chromos." In 1874, he began producing greeting cards for the popular market in England and began selling the Christmas card in the United States the next year. Also in 1874, Prang began publishing books for drawing and elementary art study for public schools. This latter activity proved so successful that he formed the Prang Educational Company in 1882.
Scope and Content Note
Art historian Mary Margaret Sittig's research material on Louis Prang dates from 1860 to 1978 and measures 3.5 linear feet. Found within the papers are biographical material for Louis Prang and for Mary Margaret Sittig, collected letters from various members of the Prang family, and scattered letters to Sittig from friends. Additional collected research materials include scattered personal business records for Louis Prang and his wife, notes and writings, art work, printed material, and photographs.
Biographical material concerning Louis Prang includes a record book and genealogy listing Prang family members, ephemera, and scattered family papers. Biographical material concerning Mary Margaret Sittig includes resumes, a photograph of Sitting, and scattered ephemera. Letters primarily consist of scattered communications between miscellaneous Prang family members, and a few business-related letters. Letters to Mary Margaret Sittig are primarily from friends and discuss her research activities. Personal business records consist of an account book for Louis Prang's wife, Rosa, and miscellaneous receipts for Louis Prang.
Notes and writings primarily consist of photocopies of research material on Louis Prang collected by Mary Margaret Sittig and include a typescript of her thesis L. Prang and Company, Fine Art Publishers. Art work consists of ink drawings, watercolor sketches, an etching, a block print, and an oil painting on fabric.
Printed material concerning Louis Prang includes clippings, commercial lithographs of book illustrations, chromolithographs of ceramics from the Walters Collection, and printed reproductions of work by others.
Photographs are of Louis Prang, his wives Rosa Prang and Mary Dana Hicks Prang, miscellaneous Prang family members, and of scattered art work. There is also the Prang Family Photograph Album that contains annotations, but no photographs.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged as 7 series:
Series 1: Biographical Material, 1881-1973 (Box 1; 10 folders)
Series 2: Letters, 1864-1974 (Box 1; 23 folders)
Series 3: Personal Business Records, 1875-1917 (Box 1; 2 folders)
Series 4: Notes and Writings, 1890-1978 (Box 1; 16 folders)
Series 5: Art Work, circa 1880 (Box 1; 9 folders)
Series 6: Printed Material, 1866-1972 (Box 1-8; 2.5 linear feet)
Series 7: Photographs, 1860-1957 (Box 3, 7; 6 folders)
Names and Subject Terms
This collection is indexed in the online catalog of the Archives of American Art under the following terms:
Subjects:
Heinzen, Rosa Prang; Prang, Louis, 1824-1909; L. Prang & Co.
Subjects-Topical:
Art historians--Pennsylvania; Chromolithography; Greeting cards industry; Lithographers; Lithography
Types of Materials:
Drawings; Etchings; Paintings; Photographs; Prints; Watercolors
Series Descriptions/Container Listing
- Biographical Material, 1881-1973, Series 1:; (Box 1; 10 folders)
  Biographical material concerning Louis Prang includes listings of Prang family members, a certificate of esteem for Louis Prang, a ship's passenger list, material from Prang's funeral and from the funeral of his mother, and an employment application for Prang's granddaughter Henriette Heinzen. Biographical material concerning Mary Margaret Sittig includes resumes, application forms for federal employment, receipts, and a photograph of Sittig.
  - Prang Family Record Book, 1891 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - A Genealogical List of Prang Family Members, a Certificate of Esteem for Louis Prang, and a Passenger List from the Ship Columbia, 1881-1900 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Booklet "Addresses at the Memorial Services of Mrs. Rosa Prang," 1898 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Miscellaneous Material Concerning the Funeral of Louis Prang, 1909 (Box 1, Folder 4-5)
  - Employment Application of Henriette Heinzen, 1933 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Biographical Material Concerning Mary Margaret Sittig, 1961-1973, (4 folders) (Box 1, Folder 7-10)
- Letters, 1864-1974, Series 2:; (Box 1; 23 folders)
  Letters primarily consist of scattered communications between miscellaneous Prang family members. Letters to Mary Margaret Sittig are primarily from friends and discuss her research activities.
  - Letters to the Prang and Heinzen Families from Unidentified Correspondents, circa 1860-circa 1978 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Letters to the Prang and Heinzen Families from Correspondents with Unknown Surnames, circa 1860-circa 1978 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Letters to the Prang and Heinzen Families from Correspondents with Surnames "A" - "O," circa 1860-circa 1978 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Letters to the Prang and Heinzen Families from Correspondents with Surnames "P," circa 1860-circa 1978 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - 15 Letters to the Prang and Heinzen Families from Correspondents with Surnames "R" - "Z," circa 1860-circa 1978 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Letters to the Prang and Heinzen Families, 1864-1887 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Letters to the Prang and Heinzen Families, 1891-1899 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Letters to the Prang and Heinzen Families, 1900-1903 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Letters to the Prang and Heinzen Families, 1904-1908 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Letters to the Prang and Heinzen Families, 1909-1912 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Letters to the Prang and Heinzen Families, 1913-1914 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Letters to the Prang and Heinzen Families, 1915-1923 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Letters to the Prang and Heinzen Families, 1924-1927 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Letters to the Prang and Heinzen Families, 1928 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Letters to the Prang and Heinzen Families, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Letters to Mary Margaret Sittig, circa 1860-circa 1978 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Letters to Mary Margaret Sittig, 1968-1969 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Letters to Mary Margaret Sittig, 1970, (3 folders) (Box 1, Folder 28-30)
  - Letters to Mary Margaret Sittig, 1971, (2 folders) (Box 1, Folder 31-32)
  - Letters to Mary Margaret Sittig, 1973-1974 (Box 1, Folder 33)
- Personal Business Records, 1875-1917, Series 3:; (Box 1; 2 folders)
  Personal business records consist of an account book for Louis Prang's wife, Rosa, and miscellaneous receipts for Louis Prang.
  - Account Book for Rosa M. Prang, 1875 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Miscellaneous Receipts for Louis Prang, 1899-1917 (Box 1, Folder 35)
- Notes and Writings, 1890-1978, Series 4:; (Box 1; 16 folders)
  Notes and writings primarily consist of photocopies of research material on Louis Prang collected by Mary Margaret Sittig, but include a typescript of her thesis L. Prang and Company, Fine Art Publishers, compilations of writings and poems by Henriette Heinzen, and miscellaneous notes by members of the Prang and Heinzen families.
  - Hand-made Book "School Reminiscences" by Henriette Heinzen, circa 1860-circa 1978 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Henriette Heinzen's Album of Poems and Inserted Printed Material, 1899-1931, (4 folders) (Box 1, Folder 37-40)
  - Miscellaneous Notes by Members of the Prang and Heinzen Families, 1890, circa 1860-circa 1978 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Notes by Sittig: Photocopy of 1869 Article "What Pictures Shall I Hang on My Walls?" by Harriet Beecher Stowe, circa 1860-circa 1978 (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Notes by Sittig: Photocopy of Microfilm of an 1875 Catalog of Art Sale from the Louis Prang Collection, circa 1860-circa 1978 (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - Notes by Sittig: Photocopy of Microfilm of an 1893 Auction Catalog, circa 1860-circa 1978 (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - Notes by Sittig: Photocopy of an 1892 Art Work Catalog Collection of L. Prang and Company of Boston, circa 1860-circa 1978 (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - Notes by Sittig: Photocopy of 1899 Catalog Louis Prang's Collection of Oil and Water-Color Paintings, circa 1860-circa 1978 (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - Thesis Typescript L. Prang and Company, Fine Art Publishers by Mary Margaret Sittig, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - Notes by Sittig: Photocopy of Typescript "Kingly Print: An American Chromo" by Lucy E. Leitzell, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 48)
  - Notes by Sittig: Photocopy of Indiana Historical Society Lectures, Autographed by Lillian B. Miller, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 49)
  - Miscellaneous Notes by Sittig, 1978, circa 1860-circa 1978, (2 folders) (Box 1, Folder 50-51)
- Art Work, circa 1880, Series 5:; (Box 1; 9 folders)
  Art work includes ink drawings, watercolor sketches primarily of floral borders, young girls, and scenic views, an etching signed by Ellen Day Hale, a block print of a Native American design, and an oil portrait painting of an unidentified man on fabric.
  - Ink Drawings, circa 1880 (Box 1, Folder 52)
  - Watercolor Sketches, circa 1880, (6 folders) (Box 1, Folder 53-58)
  - Etching Signed by Ellen Day Hale, circa 1880 (Box 1, Folder 59)
  - Block Print of a Native American Design, circa 1880 (Box 1, Folder 60)
  - Oil Portrait Painting on Fabric, circa 1860-circa 1978 (Box 5, Folder 1)
- Printed Material, 1866-1972, Series 6:; (Box 1-8; 2.5 linear feet)
  Printed material includes clippings, commercial lithographs of book illustrations, chromolithographs of ceramics from the Walters Collection and of work by others, The Card Autograph Album by L. Prang and Co., color lithographs of miniature pictures of mammals, birds, fish, insects, and miscellaneous subjects, calendars, miscellaneous greeting cards including salesmen's sample books of cards, programs, labels, and advertising cards. There are chromolithographed and block-printed fabric items including fabric squares, a fabric-covered box, shawls, and fabric-covered portfolio covers displaying images primarily of flowers and young girls. The books published by L. Prang and Co. include Prang's Standard Alphabets, American Text-Books of Art Education, The Prang Elementary Course in Art Instruction, Illustrations of the History of Art, and Yawcob's Dribulatons that is autographed by Charles Follen Adams (a.k.a. Yawcob Strauss). Books published by others are primarily German children's books with fine illustrations. There is also a large portfolio of machine-cut stencil designs.
  - Clippings, circa 1860-circa 1978 (Box 1, Folder 61)
  - Clippings, 1918-1946 (Box 1, Folder 62)
  - Clippings, 1952-1972 (Box 1, Folder 63)
  - Commercial Lithographs of Book Illustrations, circa 1860-circa 1978 (Box 1, Folder 64)
  - Chromolithographs of Ceramics from the Walters Collection, circa 1860-circa 1978, (4 folders; Oversized Material Housed in Box 4) (Box 1, Folder 65-68)
  - Chromolithographs of Art Work by Others, 1866-1903, circa 1860-circa 1978, (5 folders; Oversized Material Housed in Box 4) (Box 1, Folder 69-73)
  - The Card Autograph Album by L. Prang and Co., 1871 (Box 1, Folder 74)
  - Color Lithographs of Miniature Pictures of Mammals, circa 1860-circa 1978 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Color Lithographs of Miniature Pictures of Birds, circa 1860-circa 1978 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Color Lithographs of Miniature Pictures of Fish and Sea Creatures, circa 1860-circa 1978 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Color Lithographs of Miniature Pictures of Insects, circa 1860-circa 1978 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Color Lithographs of Miniature Pictures of Miscellaneous Subjects, circa 1860-circa 1978 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Calendars, 1888-1952, (2 folders; Oversized Material Housed in OV 8) (Box 2, Folder 6-7)
  - New Year's Cards, circa 1860-circa 1978 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Valentine's Day Cards, circa 1882-1893, (3 folders) (Box 2, Folder 9-11)
  - Easter Cards, 1880s, (2 folders) (Box 2, Folder 12-13)
  - Christmas Cards, circa 1881-1890, (4 folders) (Box 2, Folder 14-17)
  - Birthday Cards, 1870s-1890s (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Miscellaneous Printed Cards, circa 1870-1887, (3 folders; Oversized Material Housed in Box 4) (Box 2, Folder 19-21)
  - Programs, 1881-1903, (2 folders; Oversized Material Housed in Box 4) (Box 2, Folder 22-23)
  - Miscellaneous Labels and Advertising Cards, circa 1860-circa 1978, (Oversized Material Housed in OV 8) (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Chromolithographed and Block-Printed Fabric Items, circa 1860-circa 1978, (2 folders; Oversized Material Housed in Box 5 and Box 6) (Box 2, Folder 25-26)
  - Book Prang's Standard Alphabets, circa 1860-circa 1978 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Book Prang's Prize Babies, circa 1860-circa 1978 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Book Language of Flowers, Illustrated by Kate Greenaway, circa 1860-circa 1978 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Book Prang's Natural History Series for Children, 1878 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Books American Text-Books of Art Education, Numbers 2-7 and 9, Published by L. Prang and Co., 1879-1888, (7 folders) (Box 2, Folder 31-37)
  - Book Der Kinder Wundergarten by Friedrich Hofmann, 1882 (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - Book Prinzessin Wunderhold by J. Trojan, 1883 (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - Book Drei Gute Freunde, 1884 (Box 2, Folder 40)
  - Book A Gay Day for 7 by Mrs. Rose Mueller Sprague, Published by L. Prang and Co., 1887 (Box 2, Folder 41)
  - Book Autograph Recipes Published by L. Prang and Co., 1888 (Box 2, Folder 42)
  - Book The Baby's Bouquet by Walter Crane, 1890 (Box 2, Folder 43)
  - Book Das Schönste UBC Buch für die Jugend, 1890 (Box 2, Folder 44)
  - Book Yawcob's Dribulatons, Published by L. Prang and Co., 1894 (Box 2, Folder 45)
  - Book Flora's Feast by Walter Crane, 1895 (Box 2, Folder 46)
  - Book Dream Pansies by Bessie Gray, 1897 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Books The Prang Elementary Course in Art Instruction, 1897-1898, (2 folders) (Box 3, Folder 2-3)
  - Oversized Commercial Lithograph of Abraham Lincoln, 1865 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Oversized Chromolithographs of Ceramics from the Walters Collection, circa 1860-circa 1978, (from Box 1, Folder 68) (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Oversized Chromolithographs of Art Work by Others, circa 1866-1869, (from Box 1, Folder 73) (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Two Oversized Salesmen's Sample Books of Miscellaneous Cards, circa 1860-circa 1978, (from Box 2, Folder 19) (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Five Oversized Miscellaneous Printed Cards, 1870-1884, (from Box 2, Folder 21) (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Two Copies of Oversized Program The Prang Souvenir, 1881, (from Box 2, Folder 22) (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Two Oversized Chromolithographed and Embroidered Shawls (?) and a Chromolithographed Portfolio Cover; Oversized Fabric-Covered Portfolio Decorated with a Block Print Design, circa 1860-circa 1978, (from Box 2, Folder 25) (Box 5, Folder 2-5)
  - Oversized Chromolithographed Fabric-Covered Box; Eight Chromolithographed Fabric Squares, circa 1860-circa 1978, (from Box 2, Folder 25) (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Oversized Books Illustrations of the History of Art, Series 1 - IV, 1879, (4 folders) (Box 7, Folder 1-4)
  - Oversized Portfolio of Machine-Cut Stencil Designs, circa 1860-circa 1978, (2 folders) (Box 7, Folder 5-6)
  - Oversized Calendar Page, 1952, (from Box 2, Folder 7) (Box OV 8)
  - Oversized Advertisement for Prang's Valentines, circa 1860-circa 1978, (from Box 2, Folder 24) (Box OV 8)
- Photographs, 1860-1957, Series 7:; (Box 3, 7; 6 folders)
  Photographs are of Louis Prang, miscellaneous Prang family members, and scattered art work including the painting The Valley of Wyoming by Jasper Cropsey, and a still life arrangement of a table setting signed by Antoinette Perrett. There is also the Prang Family Photograph Album that contains annotations, but no photographs.
  - Prang Family Photograph Album, circa 1860 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Photographs of Louis Prang, Rosa Prang, and Mary Dana Hicks Prang, 1905, circa 1860-circa 1978, (Oversized Material Housed in Box 7) (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Photographs of Miscellaneous Prang Family Members, 1925-1957, circa 1860-circa 1978 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Photograph of Painting The Valley of Wyoming by Jasper Cropsey, circa 1860-circa 1978 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Photograph of Drawing of an Unidentified Woman and of a Lithograph of an Unidentified Man, circa 1860-circa 1978 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Oversized Photograph of Louis Prang, circa 1860-circa 1978, (from Box 3, Folder 5) (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Oversized Photograph of a Still Life Arrangement of a Table Setting Signed by Antoinette Perrett, circa 1860-circa 1978 (Box 7, Folder 7)